[SPEAKER_01]: So, can a lay lifestyle lead to becoming an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: A lay lifestyle?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The question, yeah, that's often, often asked is, can a layman be an arahant?
[SPEAKER_00]: But that depends what's meant by layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you mean that somebody is not formally ordained, doesn't wear robes, then yes, a layman can become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if by a layman you mean partaking in the lifestyle of a layman, living in company, still having concerns with the world, living a household life, not being sense-restrained, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, a layman cannot be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when the sūtra's a layman, as in a person not ordained in the big order, but became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wasn't a householder who became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a person who wasn't ordained, but wasn't living as a householder either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the most famous case is Bhāgya.
[SPEAKER_00]: who himself was a naked, a wood-bark ascetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was just wearing wood-bark to cover himself, and he was living very austerely, mindfully, practicing for who knows how long, and he was so pure that he himself thought he's fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the deva, out of compassion, said, no, actually, you're not fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go and meet the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... that's the famous instruction where the Buddha, all he needed to say to him was, in the scene, let there just be the scene, in the herd, let there just be the herd, and so on, for all the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, technically, he was a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wasn't... he wasn't a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: He wasn't an ordained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then he asked the Buddha, oh, can I join your order?
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, yeah, go and find the ball and
[SPEAKER_00]: So, technically, he was a layman who became an arahant, but you realize he was far from living a layman's life.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was basically a type of summoner, an ascetic, just not ordained in the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: And often that's where the lines get blurred.
[SPEAKER_00]: People say, oh, so you don't need to be a monk, as in you don't need to be formally ordained to become an arahant, means I can live a household life and become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to live like a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you wear robes and you're ordained formally or not, that doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the lifestyle of somebody who has renounced the world, who is sense-restrained, well, that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is a necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does constitute a summoner?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense-restraint, celibacy, seclusion, devoted to seclusion, as much as possible, and not being engaged, preoccupied, concerned, inspired by worldly affairs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might need to do some worldly things to some extent, even as monks you have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh... that's one thing, doing it as a... like a chore, and doing it because you're still driven by it, and you still want it, and you still have desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that... that must be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, technically, you can live a lay life, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were able to live lay life, yet be so withdrawn from everything, succeeding that, why don't you just become a monk?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing would stop you from becoming a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, usually, when somebody doesn't become a monk, it's because something is still stopping them in the world, which is a form of concern.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, in itself, is an impediment for if they want to be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, one can go forth without ordaining.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but not because you feel like you've gone forth, but because you actually became Sotāpanna or higher.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the noble Arya Saṅgha in the suttas includes lay people.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were not monks, but they were actually Aryas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, consequently, one can go forth and ordain and still be a householder in his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wearing robes is not a guarantee that you will
[SPEAKER_00]: That you are a samana, that you have that distinction of a noble saṅgha.